Hello everybody, this is Awi Hawkins and we have a special guest tonight, John Kiriaku
who is one of the significant whistleblowers and we will get to that in a minute. I first
have to report some sad news. Many of you met an activist here in Syracuse named Nikita Slade
when we had her on this live stream, Angela and I, to talk about organizing and we're really in
shock here in Syracuse and around the movement because she died suddenly last week from a
heart attack. She was only 32 and she's somebody who was active in our Syracuse Green Party here.
She was on the staff for my 2014 campaign for New York Governor. She was an advisor on
policing and racial justice issues for our presidential campaign and she was a key
leader in Black Lives Matter Syracuse and she also did a queer women of color podcast
that was one of Angela's favorites. She was a union millwright but to me she was the best
activist I have met from her generation. You know she was one of the most well-read
activists of any generation. I had many conversations with her on social theory and
organizing and she'd read a lot of books that I haven't found anybody else to talk to about
so I'm going to miss her for those conversations as much as her energy and commitment to the
movement and we were blessed for the contributions she made while she was with us
and we're just so sad that she's departed and she had a lot more to give so
you know that's the sad news and Angela and I wrote a little remembrance on the website.
If you go there under the updates you can you can read about it there's some pictures
there's links to the interviews I did an interview with her after a Black Lives Matter
demonstration here in Syracuse and you'll see how much she was giving and it's you know how
sad it is that she's not with us anymore. So that's just sad news to report. So what we
want to talk about tonight is the war on whistleblowers and I'm wearing my Ralph
Nader T-shirt from 08 if you can see that. Ralph coined the term whistleblowers as we
understand it today. He had a big conference and a book you know trying to promote people in
government and in the corporate sector to release information that ought to be in the
public domain in the public interest and he had a big impact you know that became part of the
ethic of people that wanted to you know do good and eventually one of the last piece of legislation
is that able to help shepherd through Congress was the whistleblowers protection act in 1989
although that has been weakened by court decisions particularly with respect to people
releasing information that's in the national security realm so most of the war on whistleblowers
that we're familiar with now are people charged under the espionage act except they're not
doing espionage they're releasing information that they think the public ought to know but
the espionage act was enacted in 1917 during World War I to go after the anti-war movement
and one of the really debilitating repressive features of it is
if you release information you can't defend it as in the public interest that's not permitted
under the statute which makes whistleblowers for charge for espionage which they're not
working for any foreign government that puts them in a real bind and so back in 19 around World War
I they charged the anti-war radicals Emma Goldman and Alexander Bergman the anarchists were deported
to Russia three socialists were charged under it one was a member of Congress Victor Berger
now there was a Philip Randolph who we know is a civil rights leader later in the century
and then Eugene Debs who was actually sentenced to 10 years for an anti-war speech he gave in
camp in Ohio I wrote a remembrance of that on the anniversary I think last year he ended up
spending three years in jail and then he was pardoned by President Harding who invited him to
the White House very different than the treatment our whistleblowers are getting to date you
know Harding took the place of Wilson it was rarely used for the rest of the century a couple
espionage cases the most notable is the Rosenbergs case and while Julius may have been giving atomic
information to the Russians it seems evidence shows that his wife Ethel was not but she was
executed as well but then it was used for the first time against whistleblowers
by Richard Nixon going against Daniel Ellsberg and Anthony Russo for releasing the Pentagon papers
and they were not convicted because of FBI misconduct and then it laid dormant again
until the administration of Barack Obama and he went after eight different people
for leaking information mostly about our military and intelligence operations
and you've heard of so many people Chelsea Manning who released all those
informations including that infamous collateral murder video which showed this guy on a helicopter
gunship killing civilians asking for permission seemed to be you know excited about it reminded
me of the first Vietnam vet I talked to back in 1964 he's the older brother of a
literally league teammate who was bragging about how he was just killing random people from
his helicopter in Vietnam and that massacre not only killed civilians it killed some Reuters
journalists and so Chelsea you know I spent time in prison for that they've still
you know asked her to do more and she's spent more time in prison
uh in that same first group of eight under Obama Edward Snowden is probably the best known he's
somebody his book on uh what do you call it uh I forget the name came out in 2019 it was the
most impactful book I read that year and I was saying during the campaign I would drop the
charges and bring him into the administration because I felt he had the right values he
was for democracy against authoritarianism and had a handle on how to do you know proper
intelligence without violating people's constitutional rights and you know if I was
president I would need somebody who knew how to do that and then another one is our guest tonight
John Kiriakou who revealed to journalists information about the CIA's torture program
during the early 2000s and then uh Obama I mean Trump continued uh Obama administration declined
to prosecute Julian Assange Trump is going ahead and Biden has continued and there are a number
of other cases going on right now that we'll probably talk about tonight like Daniel Hale
and then the last thing I want to say before I bring on John Kiriakou is that it's not
only the Espionage Act we have a case with Stephen Donziger uh his he had a trial open up yesterday
and this is a man who worked with 30 000 farmers and indigenous people in Ecuador
and won a 9.5 or 8.5 billion dollars in damages from Chevron for environmental and health
of damages in Ecuador in 2011 and right away Chevron sued in this country and
they charged him with things like saying he extorted and bribed and so forth the process in Ecuador
and so by 2014 he didn't get a jury trial he just had a judge rule that the Ecuadorian
ruling should be vacated and find Donziger 800 000 dollars and then in the appeal
uh the judge asked for you know his phone and computer and whatnot
which Donziger said that's uh attorney client privilege so he charged him with contempt of
court which led to his disbarment and house arrest now march this year the second court of
circuit court of appeals vacated some of the sanctions against Donziger I included house arrest
because of this uh
So that went to trial yesterday and already a couple of the chevron lawyers have dropped out because in cross examination
The lies they've been giving would be exposed. That's that's what the theory is
So
Now it's and the prosecution is being done by a private prosecutor
Because the southern district of New York the US Attorney said there's not a case and refused to
To prosecute so there's a lot of shady stuff going on here and progressive Democrats just sent a letter to
Mayor Garland to look into this case. It's got a lot of attention
People are wondering where Barack Obama is. He went to law school with Stephen Donziger. They played basketball together Obama's been silent
Ralph Nader had a podcast that's worth listening. I think in late March
I think in late March with Stephen Donziger
But you can see what the issue is here
He won a big judgments again against the corporation and they went to the US courts
which acted like their lackeys and
Basically took this man's life from him and you know, he's fighting to get it back in court
And it's a case we should all be following so
That's what we're talking about with whistleblowers. It's really difficult to be a whistleblower
You put your whole life on the line and that book by
Ed Snowden his permanent record
So I had forgot that
So let's let's bring John Kiriakou on and he can talk about
His experience as a whistleblower and he knows a lot of these whistleblowers
We haven't named all of them but
We'll get to them as we go through this discussion. So welcome John. Thank you Howie. Thanks very much for having me and
Hello, everybody. I'm I'm very happy to be here. I've got a story to tell you and
I'll tell the story and I'd love to take whatever questions you might have
So I I spent 15 years at the CIA the first half of my career was in
Analysis just sort of sitting at a desk thinking the big thoughts
writing papers that nobody would read and I got bored with that and I made a very unusual transfer into
Counterterrorism operations as it turned out
I was the only person in the entire CIA who was fluent in both Greek and Arabic and they made a determination
That it was a lot easier to teach a linguist
Operations than it was to take an operations person and teach teach him how to speak Greek and Arabic
so I went into counterterrorism operations in
1997 and
In the immediate aftermath of the 9-11 attacks. I was
Named the chief of counterterrorism for the CIA in Pakistan
So in that position high stress
Dangerous position. I led a series of raids in March of 2002 that resulted in the
capture of
Well, I'm not allowed to say the actual number still but it was many dozens of Al Qaeda fighters
Including one by the name of Abu Zubaydah who we believed at the time was the number three in Al Qaeda
He was not the number three. He was actually never even a member of Al Qaeda
He was certainly a bad guy. He
Assisted Al Qaeda in terms of logistics, you know, if if you were
Tired of the fight and you wanted to take it home
Abu Zubaydah would get it for you. Abu Zubaydah
Created and ran the two Al Qaeda training camps in southern Afghanistan. He formed the what was called the House of Martyrs
Safe house in Peshawar Pakistan. So bad guy, but not a member of Al Qaeda and certainly not the number three in Al Qaeda
but on the night of March 22nd 2002 we caught him and
a Pakistani policeman shot him three times with an AK-47 in the thigh the groin and the stomach and
He was very severely wounded. My orders were to
sit next to his bed
24-7 George Tenet told me
24-7 CIA eyes on he said do not leave his bedside and so I I sat there
24 hours after we caught him
Abu Zubaydah came out of his coma and
The first thing he said to me was he asked me to kill him
He asked me to take a pillow and smother him and I said I said, oh, no, Abu Zubaydah
We've been we've been looking for you for a long time
Nobody's gonna kill you. In fact, I said you're gonna get the best medical care that the American government could provide
He cried a lot. He said that he would never know the touch of a woman
he would never know the joy of fatherhood and
And we talked a lot about
religion
He recited poetry
He asked if I would pass a message to his mother
And finally I said listen, I'm gonna give you some advice. I
Am the nicest guy that you're gonna meet in this experience
My colleagues are not nice like I am
So if there's one thing that you do, it's that you have to cooperate
There were 50,000 people in those towers that morning. I said you're not the victim here
and he said to me you seem like a nice man, but you're the enemy and
I'll never cooperate
so another well altogether 56 hours passed I was with him for 56 hours and
and
A CIA plane flew in to pick him up and take him to what turned out to be a secret prison that none of us knew about we
We didn't have a need to know and we weren't read into the
Into the compartment. So he asked me to hold his hand three FBI agents and I carried him out to the plane on
on a gurney and
We we tied him across the luggage rack at the back of the plane and I leaned over and I said remember
You have to cooperate. Good luck. I told him and I squeezed his hand. Never saw him again
three months later, I've returned to CIA headquarters and
and
Certainly, I was a beta was not cooperating
But I was in the cafeteria one day standing in line to get lunch and a senior officer from the CIA's counterterrorism center
Stopped me and said hey very casually. Hey, I'm glad I ran into you
Do you want to be certified in the use of enhanced interrogation techniques?
I had never heard that term before this was all this was sorry May the 6th
2002 I still remember the date
So I said enhanced interrogation techniques techniques. What does that mean and very excitedly?
He he said we're gonna start getting rough with these guys
And I said well, what exactly does that mean and so he explained to me these different techniques
And I said man, that sounds like a torture program
I I've got a I've got a moral and ethical problem with that besides the fact the tortures illegal
the fact of the matter is
We have something in this country called the Federal Torture Act of 1946
Which specifically outlaws specifically outlaws
Exactly those techniques that we used against Al Qaeda prisoners
Besides that we were
signatories to and the drafters of the United Nations Convention Against Torture now in
1946 we executed Japanese soldiers who waterboarded American POWs
That was a death penalty crime to waterboard somebody
in 1968 January 11th 1968 the Washington Post ran a front page
photograph of an American soldier waterboarding a North Vietnamese prisoner on the day that that photo appeared
Secretary of Defense McNamara ordered an investigation the soldier was arrested
He was charged with torture and he was sentenced to 20 years in prison
Well, the law never changed
We changed
So something that was a death penalty offense in
1946 something that called for 20 years in prison in
1968 was not just
Okay by 2002 it was actively encouraged and supported by both the Justice Department and the White House and
Then carried out by the Central Intelligence Agency. I
Said this was illegal
It was immoral and it was unethical and I wanted no part of it on August 1st
2002 the CIA began to torture Abu Zubeda and they began with the technique of waterboarding which was one of the
harshest
Techniques that they had
Certainly there were people inside the CIA who objected to this but the key phrase here is inside the CIA
Nobody said anything publicly nothing not a word. I
Was promoted at the time because I had caught up with Zubeda
And so I became the executive assistant to the CIA's deputy director for operations and in that capacity
I saw literally every cable
that was coming into the CIA from around the world and so I was reading the reporting coming back
from the secret site where I was a beta had been taken.
And CIA officers went far beyond what had been authorized by the Justice Department. There
were a couple of techniques that they were using that I believed at the time and still to this
day that were worse than than waterboarding. One was sleep deprivation. Now sleep deprivation sounds
like no big deal, right? They keep you awake. But it's not that simple. What they do is they
they chain you to an eyeball in the ceiling so you can't sit or kneel or lay or get comfortable
in any way. They have industrial power lights on you 24 hours a day and they're
blasting music over and over and over the same song over and over again 24 hours a day.
Now we know from the American Psychological Association, the APA, which has done studies
on these kinds of things that people begin to lose their minds around day seven with no sleep.
They begin to die around day nine and that's because your organs begin to shut down
from lack of sleep. The CIA though was authorized to keep prisoners awake for up to 12 days.
Now we killed people with that technique of sleep deprivation. There was nothing in the
Justice Department's opinion that said we could murder people but they did it anyway.
The other one was was called the cold cell. The cold cell was an absolutely horrible thing.
They chain you to that eyeball in the ceiling again. They chill your cell to 50 degrees Fahrenheit.
They strip you naked and then every hour a CIA officer goes into your cell and throws a bucket
of ice water on you. We killed two more prisoners with that technique. So this was ongoing and
at the same time the CIA was collecting literally no intelligence from any of these
prisoners. Certainly they were babbling on about whatever it was they thought the CIA wanted to
hear just to get them to stop the torture but the analysts and the collectors were not able
to collect any actionable intelligence at all. Nothing. I resigned from the CIA in early 2004
and I was waiting for somebody to say something because I just assumed that this was so heinous
and there were certainly other people inside the agency that were opposed to it. I just
expected somebody to come out and say something. Nobody said a word. Finally in December of
2007 five and a half years after I got home from Pakistan and more than five years after we started
torturing Abu Zubaydah I got a call from Brian Ross at ABC News and he said that someone had told him
a source had told him that I had tortured Abu Zubaydah. I said that was absolutely untrue. I
was the only person who was kind to Abu Zubaydah. I have never raised a hand to a prisoner in my life.
I said your source is either mistaken or he's lying and I came to the conclusion later that the
source was lying because it turned out the source was at the White House. So I decided
that now was the time to come clean that the American people owned this information. The
American people had a right to know what their government was doing in their name.
Besides the fact that it is illegal it is a felony to classify a crime and what I mean by that is
if you are doing something that is a crime whether in the United States or under international law
it is illegal to make that operation classified. By definition because it's a crime it has to remain
unclassified and so on December 11th 2007 I gave a nationally broadcast interview with Brian Ross
at ABC News and I said three things that just changed the course of the rest of my life.
I said that the CIA was torturing its prisoners. I said that torture was official
US government policy. It was not the result of a rogue CIA officer as President Bush had said
disingenuously and I said that the torture program had been personally approved by the
president himself. As you might imagine within 24 hours the CIA reported me to the FBI.
They filed something called a crimes report saying that I had leaked classified information
to the media. The FBI investigated me for a full year from December of 2007 until December of 2008
and then they sent my attorney something called a declination letter declining to prosecute me.
They said that I had not violated the law. Four weeks later Barack Obama becomes president
and he appoints John Brennan an old nemesis of mine to be the deputy national security advisor
for counterterrorism. I had no idea that John Brennan secretly asked the justice department
to reopen the case against me and so for the next three years my phones were tapped,
my emails were intercepted and teams of FBI agents followed me not all the time
but followed me periodically wherever to the grocery store, to church, to a restaurant
with my family. They followed me to my to my mom's sister's funeral in Ohio. I actually didn't know it
was them and I reported it to the FBI thinking maybe it's a terrorist, maybe it's a criminal,
you know who knows. Here it was the FBI and I reported it to the FBI. So in January 2012
this all came to a head and I was arrested and charged with five felonies including three counts
of espionage. Now as how we pointed out espionage is one of the gravest crimes with which an American
can be charged and in many cases it carries with it the death penalty. I knew in my heart
I hadn't committed espionage talking to ABC News or really talking to the American people
via ABC News is not espionage and so I hired a team of A-list nationally known national security
attorneys here in Washington and we decided we were going to fight. Now let's talk about that
espionage act for a minute. How we mentioned that the espionage act was was written and
passed into law in 1917 the stated purpose at the time was to combat German saboteurs during the
first world war. It was never used against German saboteurs it was used against progressives and
anti-war activists but between 1917 and 2009 the espionage act was used to prosecute three people
who had spoken to the media right now how we mentioned correctly that it was used against other
political opponents of whatever president happened to be in office but three people
were prosecuted for speaking to the media. Just under Barack Obama eight Americans
were charged with espionage for speaking to the media. Barack Obama had what I would describe
as a Nixonian obsession with leaks. The New York Times said that the point of my prosecution
was not even really to prosecute me it was not even really to punish me it was to frighten
every other person in the national security apparatus from going to the public from going
to the press to discuss waste fraud abuse illegality or threats to the public health or public
safety which is the definition of whistleblowing the legal definition and certainly Scott Shane
at the New York Times told me that on the day of my arrest every single one of the New York
Times national security sources went silent and stayed silent. It's kind of a long story
but I'm going to skip a lot of it we could talk about it in the questions and answers
what ended up happening was this I was facing 45 years in prison in my first meeting with the
Justice Department that's what they offered me 45 years and one of the Justice Department's
lawyers said take the plea Mr. Kiriakou and you may live to meet your grandchildren I said
I'm not doing 45 minutes later on they came down to 10 years on a Monday 10 years they said take a
guilty plea to espionage and do 10 years I said I didn't commit espionage and I haven't done
anything to be ashamed of on Wednesday two days later they came down to eight years
years. And then on Friday, they came down to five years. My lead attorney was a giant
by the name of Plato Kacheris. And Plato said, these were his exact words. I've been a practicing
attorney in Washington for 52 years. And he said, I've never seen them come down in time.
He said, usually they'll offer you 10. If you turn it down, they offer you 15.
If you turn it down, they offer you 18. And I said, well, why are they coming down in time
with me? And very quickly he said, because they have a shit case and they know it's shit.
So I said, well, what do we do? He said, we fight and we go to trial. You didn't do anything
wrong. The truth of the matter is, according to ProPublica, which did a study published
in November of 2012, the federal government wins 98.2% of its cases. Almost all of those
are a result of two techniques that the Justice Department uses. One is called charge stacking,
and the other is venue shopping. Now venue shopping is easy. They charge you in the
federal district where you are most likely to be convicted and where you are most
likely to get a long sentence. That's why I was charged in the eastern district of Virginia.
It's called the espionage court because no national security defendant has ever won a case there.
That's where they charged Jeffrey Sterling. That's where they charged Chelsea Manning.
That's where they charged, well, Chelsea Manning was military, but her contempt was
eastern district. That's where they charged Ed Snowden and Julian Assange. The other one
I said is charge stacking. So what they'll do is they'll charge you. Let's say maybe
you did do something wrong, but they won't charge you with one crime. They'll charge
you with 10, 20 felonies, and they'll wait until you go bankrupt, and then they'll
come and say, all right, listen, we'll drop all the charges if you plead guilty
to one felony. Well, what are you going to do? I had five kids at home. I knew that
they won 98.2% of their cases. I was facing 45 years in prison. They're offering me
now their final, their best and final offer was two and a half years. I do 23
months. So I hired OJ Simpson's jury consultant who happened to be the
uncle of my best friend's wife. Oh, no, eastern district of Virginia is in
Alexandria, Virginia in response to one of the questions. So I hired the jury
consultant and he came up and we got him, we got him a security clearance
because all my lawyers had to be cleared. He went through all 15,000
pages of discovery. And then we all met in this big conference room and he
said, if we were in any other district in America, we would win this thing. He
said, but the eastern district of Virginia, your jury is going to be made up
of people from the FBI, the CIA, the Pentagon, intelligence community
contractors and their family members. He said, you don't have a prayer.
Just take the deal. The night before I had to give the justice
department an answer, my wife and I stayed up all night long. I was only the
second American ever charged with violating the Intelligence Identities
Protection Act of 1981. And so we went over, there was no case law, but there
were several law review journals from Harvard Law School. And we concluded
that I just hadn't done anything wrong. I hadn't broken the law. And so I
came on my attorneys at six o'clock in the morning and I said, I've been
thinking about it all night and I decided I want to go to trial, thinking
stupidly that once I got in front of a jury, they would see how ridiculous
this was. They see that it was political. They would see that I had
done a public service. And my lawyers called me and said, or one of them
called me and said, put on a pot of coffee, we're on the way over. They
came over to my house. They told me, you can't turn this down. You
have to take the deal. If you're convicted, you're seriously looking
at 12 to 18 years. Just take the deal. I still didn't want to take the
deal. And then one of the attorneys, the one who I liked and respected
the most pulled me aside and said, listen, this can be a blip in your
life, or it can be the defining event in your life. Make it the blip.
And so I took the deal. It's funny that the deal, the case itself, made me far
better known than I ever would have been before. I mean, when I blew the whistle
on the torture program, it was a story for a few days a week. But my
prosecution made me a martyr for human rights. It gave me a venue
a soapbox with which I could speak to the American people. I'm on TV all the
time. Thanks to these idiots at the Justice Department. Otherwise, nobody
would even remember that there was a guy who said anything about the
torture program. I was very pleased one day when I was sitting in
prison. It was it was December of 2014. And I was reading a four day old copy
of the New York Times. They would of course, go through my New York
Times and cut out articles they didn't want me to read. But there was an
interview in there with with Ed Snowden. And Ed said that he had watched
my case, and he had watched Tom Drake's case, Tom Drake, the NSA whistle
blower. And neither one of us backed down despite the enormous pressure
that we were under. And so we had inspired him to go public with his
revelations. And I got to tell you that and one other thing that also
happened in December of 14 made it all worthwhile. The other thing was
I'm sitting there in my cell one day, and a guy walks in and says,
Hey, buddy, you're on TV. I said, Oh, okay. I got up. I walked over the TV.
And it was John McCain standing on the floor of the Senate, saying that
without my revelations, the American people would never have known that
there was a torture program, and that they were torturing people in the
name of the American people. He said, even though I was in prison,
that I deserved the thanks of the American public. And he was happy
to do that from the floor of the Senate. That completely changed the way
that I saw myself. You know, CNN, until the day before I went to prison,
called me CIA leaker, John Kiriakou. They changed it to CIA torture
whistleblower, John Kiriakou, the day before I went to prison.
Fox for whatever odd reason, probably because I was prosecuted by
Obama, always called me CIA torture whistleblower, John Kiriakou.
MSNBC, which was pretty much the Obama network, called me CIA leaker,
John Kiriakou, or John Kiriakou, who styles himself a whistleblower,
which still makes me angry to this day. But you know, this is just
the way it is. Now, what's happened since I got out of prison
in February of 2015 is all of us Obama-era whistleblowers
have sort of banded together, along with some absolutely amazing
attorneys like Jaisalyn Radak, for example, formerly of the
Government Accountability Project, now of what's called the
Whisper Program, the Whistleblower and Source Protection Program.
Tom Drake, Ed Snowden, the godfather of whistleblowing,
the great, heroic Daniel Ellsberg. There are a bunch of us,
and we're like brothers and sisters. And what we do now,
and I'm happy to do it, and I do it several times a week,
is to advise other would-be whistleblowers so that they
don't make the same mistakes that I made, or the same mistakes
that my other whistleblowing colleagues have made.
The truth has to get out there, and this is one thing about
the truth is it always eventually sees the light, right?
You can't keep the truth under wraps.
You can't trick the American people over the long term.
It's just not possible. And so I'm happy to be a part of
helping people get their truth out there.
Remember, there's a legal definition of whistleblowing.
Bringing to light any evidence of waste, fraud, abuse,
illegality, or threats to the public health or public safety.
I'm going to close by saying one thing.
At the CIA, the culture is such that they always
taught us that everything in life is a shade of gray.
That is not true. Some things are black and white.
Some things are right and wrong.
When I stood on my first day at the CIA with my hand in the air,
and I swore an oath to uphold the Constitution of the United States
and to protect it against all enemies, foreign and domestic,
I meant it. I'm sorry to say that of the 300 people in the room that day,
it appears that I was the only one who meant it, but I meant it.
And so government is better.
when government is honest government is better when it's transparent we're right and they're wrong
and we have to make them pay when they violate the law so thank you very much i kept it to 30
minutes just like i promised howie and i am happy to take whatever questions you might have for me
oh we can't hear you howie
i said thank you john i think a lot of people hearing the details in the sequence
just brings it home thank you you know because most people they maybe read something in the press and
you know when you string it together you realize how uh how oppressive the government is toward
people that tell us what's going on that we ought to know about yeah and that is a huge problem i mean
it reminds me we call ourselves a democracy it reminds me of what gandhi said when he was asked
about whether western civilization he said it would be a good idea and uh we we have a lot of things
to correct yes we do indeed so i've seen some questions in the chat there we go so sentino
musto my question to john did it rattle your nerves and or mentally scar you've seen people
being tortured and murdered did this have anything to do with you deciding to become a whistleblower
that's a really good question you know it's funny i've been answering these questions for
you know 14 years and nobody's ever asked me that um the easy answer is yes it did scar me
when i came home from from pakistan well let me back up i've got a friend who i worked with
in the cia we go to the same church and um he just happens to be a former brigadier general
and he's also a psychiatrist and um he mentioned something to me about a year ago that i it just
had never crossed my mind he said i said you know i was a star at the agency until until i i left
and he said that's not true they turned on you in 2002 i said what are you talking about
i was a star in 2002 i went up to the seventh floor i was the executive assistant and he said
don't you remember they used to call you the human rights guy i said yes he said that wasn't a compliment
they were talking about you behind your back because you weren't willing to torture anybody
or to kill anybody and another truth of that time and i kept this to myself
um was i came back from pakistan with with ptsd you know i was i was surprised at
how willing my colleagues were to kill people you know these are guys that i used to get
together with on the weekends we'd have a barbecue our kids would play together our
wives were friends and then they would go on their week-long missions and and kill people
and come back there was one guy there was one guy that i worked with i sat 20 feet away from him
in the cia's counterterrorism center and every morning i'd say hey man how you doing and every
morning you'd say hey buddy how you doing i was never really clear on exactly what he did
in the office you know we don't have like name tags or anything with your job description right
so i asked a colleague i said you know i'm unclear exactly what he does here he travels an awful lot
and my friend said john he works for the special activities division what do you think they do
and i thought wow you know what i hadn't thought of that because he's such a nice guy he's so
easy going he brings bagels in on fridays and coffee and he was an assassin and you know when
when public opinion polls show that the american people are in solid support of the cia and other
intelligence agencies killing people who they believe might perhaps maybe someday pose a threat to
the united states i mean where do you go from there you're really crying in the darkness but um yes to
answer uh santino's question uh yeah that was not my thing it bothered me very much i'll add one
other thing a cia psychiatrist a different one once told me that the cia actively seeks to hire
people who have sociopathic tendencies not sociopaths sociopaths are impossible to control
because they don't have a conscience they blow right through the the polygraph exam but you just can't
control them because they're unable to feel remorse or regret but as you might imagine
sociopaths slip through the process because they can't feel remorse because they don't react
on a polygraph well just like in corporate america those same sociopaths rise to the very top of
the cia's leadership and that's why we've got assassination squads and that's why we have
teams of people who overthrow governments or who do international kidnapping you know that's why
we need robust congressional oversight which we haven't had since the the 70s frankly good question
thank you santino jason justice asks hi john do you know how many publicly known quote intelligence
agencies there are follow-up why do we need so many when they seem to be asleep at the switch
promoters of us imperialism yes you're absolutely right in every aspect of that question jason
first of all there are no secret intelligence services anymore not since nsa finally went public the
cia of course was secret in the beginning nsa was secret like into the late 70s but what you
see is what you get i think it's like 19 of them now some are still so secret that we don't
really know what they do like darpa for example at the pentagon we know that they develop futuristic
weapons systems and stuff like that but beyond that we don't really know what goes on inside
darpa why do we need so many of them we don't we don't this is empire building on the part of
different components of the u.s government primarily the pentagon like the pentagon
is in ultimate charge of most intelligence agencies so why do we need army intelligence
navy intelligence marine core intelligence air force intelligence uh d i a uh nsa belongs to the
pentagon why why do we need all those they're duplicative they all do the same thing and then
they try to one-up each other and better each other all the while the cia is making fun of them about
how terrible they are and how amateurish but the final part of your your question is um they
seem to be asleep at the switch and promoters of us imperialism yes you're exactly right they
are asleep at the switch and listen i'm telling you from firsthand experience the cia which is
supposed to be the quote unquote best and brightest has missed literally every major international
development since the creation of the cia in 1947 they missed everything from from the building
of the berlin wall to the fall of the berlin wall and everything in between they they blew the collapse
of the uh of the soviet union they blew the collapse of the shah's regime in iran the the
directorate of operations completely blew uh democracy in iran by overthrowing prime minister
mosadic on behalf of british petroleum bp seriously kermit roosevelt for uh teddy roosevelt's son who
was in charge of that operation for the cia later said that it was the gravest mistake he had made
in his life uh my dear friend and attorney bruce fine he's he's one of the most important
uh constitutional scholars in america uh has been talking about writing a book
about the cia's analytic failures we all know about their operational failures they're terrible
operationally but the analytic failures are even more dangerous or have been more dangerous through
history because it's that analysis that our policymakers rely on to make foreign policy
and frequently the cia has been so wrong that foreign policy has been a disaster a disaster
so excellent question thank you for that yeah i would just add that there was a book came out several
years ago by william arkin and dania priest called top secret america yes fantastically an expose in
the washington post and it it describes the department of homeland security and the intelligence
agencies have become like the military industrial complex the intelligence industrial complex yes
building bureaucracies they got so much money they're spending it you know before the end of the
year so they can get you know refunded and there's a lot of waste and while they're playing without
this money they're not collecting intelligence they're like you know let me ask you a question
and this is not a rhetorical question why does the department of agriculture need an
intelligence agency why does the department of commerce need a fully staffed intelligence
agency what possible intelligence
Could they be collecting or analyzing or contributing to it doesn't make any sense to me?
You know, it's like the Department of Education has has an armed
Police unit that also collects intelligence. It's the Department of Education
Although they're not members of the the I capital I capital C intelligence community
Why do they even call themselves intelligence? This doesn't make any sense to me
Yeah, there reminds me of another book came out in the 80s about
They called it guard labor
one quarter of the workforce
security guards police
The intelligence apparatus
Is watching the other three quarters of us
I mean, it's an enormous waste
And really not in the public interest. Yeah
So, yeah, that's right. You know Ed Snowden
We wouldn't have any idea really the extent to which nsa spies on us if it hadn't been for Ed Snowden
I think he's a bona fide american hero. I really do and
Let's let's think about this for a second what nsa does
First of all nsa was not created by an act of congress
It was just arbitrarily created by the pentagon and just foisted upon us
The pentagon denied its existence until 1978
And now what they do despite the fact that in nsa's charter. They are prohibited
prohibited
From collecting information on what are called us persons
That's a us citizen or any person in the country on a green card a permanent resident alien
That's all they do now
Right, they have access to every phone call every email every text message
That every american sends and receives every single day and they have enough
space
Memory at this new facility that they just finished building in utah to collect information from every american for the next 500 years
That's not what they should be doing. They should be collecting overseas to protect us
We're not the enemy here, but that's what it's come down to
I see rob rich has a question about julian assange
i'm proud to say that i'm on the julian assange defense advisory committee and um
julian is suffering mightily right now, but
I think actually that he has the upper hand in that
The justice department has to prove
to the british supreme court that
The the way the u.s. Practices solitary confinement is not a form of torture
Now the reason why that's going to be impossible is that the united nations has already declared it to be a form of torture
And two other british courts have blocked extraditions to the united states
Of prisoners who would be subject to solitary confinement here because it's a form of torture
So there are three separate precedents
That are serving right now to protect julian assange
Now the british are being jerks about it and they won't let him out of belmarsh prison
Pending this this appeal, but honestly. I don't see how the u.s. Can win this appeal. They're gonna have to let julian go
Let's hope so let's hope so
z kramer
Do you think it is realistic to remove the institution of the cia?
Thank you for that the answer is yes, and i'll tell you why
Um, i mentioned a few minutes ago that much intelligence work is duplicative
In the cia's case. That's especially true
The cia's department or directorate of intelligence does analysis
Well, the same literally the same analysis is done by the state department's bureau of intelligence and research in our
The directorate of operations that the cia collects human source intelligence
Human source intelligence is also collected by the defense department's defense human services dhs
Uh, the cia's directorate of science and technology develops new
New weapons new systems new ways of interception
Just as both nsa and darpa do so literally everything that the cia does
Is also done somewhere else in government and at least in the case of the state department and darpa
It's done better than it's done at the cia
um, the cia in my view has become a rogue organization, especially after 9 11
and um, congress just is unwilling or unable to exercise legitimate oversight
And so I really don't believe that
We need a cia it doesn't contribute anything to the national security
It hasn't saved us from anything protected us from anything
I mean, it was the cia's failure that we had 9 11 in the first place
So no, I I don't think that we need to have a cia
Deborah susa olivera
John yeah, what can americans do to protect whistleblowers? What a great question that is
um, and and it's hard the answer is difficult it's it's um
It's something that's going to take a long time and what we have to do is to ride our elected officials
Uh to to not just you know come out in support of whistleblowers
But the laws need to be changed how we mentioned in his his introduction
Or maybe you didn't maybe how we before we started we were talking about it
and
That's the fact that whistleblowers are not permitted to present an affirmative defense
You know, I talked to ed snowden a few months ago and we were talking about the possibility of him coming home
And he said that that he's willing to come home and he's willing to go to prison
Right if he can get up in court and explain to the judge
And to the american people why he did what he did that's called an affirmative defense
Yes, I did it, but I did it for this reason
Well, the espionage act does not allow an affirmative defense
And in my own case my judge said not in a million years
Could I get up and explain why I did what I did?
Because the affirmation is irrelevant
So what we need to do is we need to very seriously amend and you know what I take that back not amend
We need to scrap the espionage act and we need to start fresh again
The espionage act is so old that it doesn't even mention
classified information
Why because it was written 40 years before the classification system was even invented
It mentions only national defense information and then it doesn't it doesn't
identify
What national defense information is it doesn't define it?
And so it's up to each individual judge
in each individual
uh
federal district
To define what national defense
information is
Well, how is that just how is that fair?
So that's what we need to do is to really ride our elected officials now. I'm not stupid. I know
I know that there's no member of congress who's going to say
Oh, you know what I should do to really win lots of new votes. I should make it more difficult to charge someone with espionage
But you know, let's be adults here and grab the bull by the horns
That's exactly what needs to be done. The whole law needs to be scrapped and rewritten
And not be used against people that aren't doing espionage, that's right. Listen the espionage act should be used
To prosecute people who commit espionage against the united states
If you're working for a foreign government china, russia, cuba, israel, whatever
Then you should be charged and prosecuted under the espionage act
But whistleblowers. No
Uh, Eugene Debs because he was against the war. No, that's not what it was meant to to be
Or that's not what it was supposed to be anyway
Diana m16
John, do you see gitmo ever being closed? Talk about cowardice, huh?
I'll tell you a quick story diane
um
When I caught my first group of prisoners it was in january of 2002
And we locked them up temporarily in the raul pindi jail just because it happened to be the nearest jail to us
And I called cia headquarters counter-terrorism center and I said listen. I caught four guys
I don't know what to do with them and they said, oh, we're gonna fly in a c12. Just put them on the c12
I said, oh, you're gonna take it back to the us for prosecution
They said no, we're gonna send them to guantanamo and I said guantanamo cuba
Yeah, I said, why would you send them to guantanamo cuba?
And the response was fascinating the response was we're going to use guantanamo as a clearing house
So that we can charge them in the federal districts
Uh in washington dc and the eastern district of virginia the southern and eastern districts of new york
And the eastern district of massachusetts
Right, so this is where the crimes were committed
They're only
going to be in Guantanamo for a matter of weeks until we can figure out which district
to send them to for their trial. And I said, oh, that's a great idea. Well, nobody ever
came to the United States for trial. Almost nobody was even charged with a crime. You
saw how the Republicans completely flipped out like crazy people when Obama said during
the 2008 campaign that he wanted to shut Guantanamo down. And in fact, they passed a law over his
veto threat that prohibit the president United States from closing down Guantanamo. There
was an article in today's Washington Post saying that the last minor prisoner is being
released from Guantanamo. He's an Afghan that leaves only one Afghan left at Guantanamo.
He's one of 70 people. And at its height it had something like 789 people, 70 people. Well,
some of them are, you know, truly bad guys like Khalid Sheikh Mohammed, the mastermind of 9-11.
But my God, even Khalid Sheikh Mohammed has constitutional rights. So either charge him
with a crime or let him go. Same with Abu Zubaydah, same with Ramzi bin Ash-Shib, same with
all these guys. If you're not going to charge them with a crime, you have to
let them go. They have the same right that you and I have to face our accusers in a court of law,
to face a jury of their peers. And if we're not going to allow them to do that,
then they have to be released. With that said, I don't see Guantanamo closing down
until either two things happen. These prisoners eventually die. And, you know,
that happens with some frequency, usually by suicide. Or somehow the government is able to
charge them in a civilian court. But the reason that hasn't happened yet is because the CIA tortured
them all. And because they were tortured, literally nothing that they said can be used against them.
And without their own admissions, then there's just nothing to hold them on.
It's a quagmire.
Tom Violet, please comment on the recent hack of Colonial Pipeline.
Yeah. So the government, I think, is saying that it was Russian. The first report I heard was
that it was Indians, Indian hackers. Now they're saying it's Russian. I've got a friend at the
FBI who says that they're pretty confident that it's not Russian government. It's, you know,
probably a handful of guys in their parents' basements or whatever. But this is bad, right?
This is bad where a couple of hackers could shut down the East Coast's major pipeline,
main pipeline, and essentially cut off the supply chain of gasoline to a half a dozen
states along the East Coast. But this comes back to the notion of what NSA should be doing.
Why didn't NSA protect us from this? Right? They're supposed to be the geniuses in this realm.
Where was NSA? I'll tell you where NSA was. They were busy reading your emails and my emails
and listening to our phone calls and trying to decide who's un-American or less American than
the next guy. But this is exactly what NSA is supposed to be doing, protecting us from
electronic enemies. And they dropped the ball.
Well, we've come upon our hour. I don't see any more questions popping up.
Excellent. So I really appreciate you coming on, John.
Howie, thanks for having me. It's always a pleasure. I've been a big fan of yours for a
long time. So I was very happy to do it. Thanks for having me. Likewise, you know,
I've been following your case for a decade now. And thank you.
This whistleblower issue is so important. And, you know, we don't have an administration
now any more than under Trump. No, it's going to deal with it. I mean,
no, the contributions of Julian Lange and Daniel Hale are going forward.
This is bipartisan. Biden is just as bad as Trump and Trump was just as bad as Obama.
And may I say one last thing? There's a very important whistleblower out there right now
by the name of Daniel Hale. Dan is the drone whistleblower who went public with the fact
that we were murdering civilians, women, children, the elderly in our drone program.
He was scooped up by the Justice Department last week, and he's incarcerated right now at a federal
holding facility in Alexandria, Virginia, of course, the Eastern District of Virginia.
And the poor guy is terrified. He's on suicide watch right now. I posted on Facebook and on
Twitter his address. So, you know, if you've got five minutes, send him a letter, send him a postcard,
just tell him that he's not forgotten. He's really going through some dark days right now.
Yeah, I hope everybody will take a minute to do that. Thank you.
So I don't even need closing comments. You're going to be on a podcast with
Jesslyn Radek, who's a whistleblower herself and a lawyer for whistleblowers next week.
You want to tell people when that's happening? Sure. Actually, let me look at my calendar
on my phone. Jesslyn Radek, I mentioned a few minutes ago, was one of my attorneys,
one of my 11 attorneys. And she is an absolute genius when it comes to these
whistleblower issues. She's a whistleblower herself. She blew the whistle on the fact that
the Justice Department had denied access to an attorney for John Walker Lind,
who was known as the American Taliban. That's going to be at 12 noon Eastern.
Go to Covert Action Magazine's website, 12 noon Eastern on Tuesday, May 18th.
Okay, good. So if people didn't get enough of you tonight, they can get more next week.
Jesslyn's more interesting than I am. And so is Tom Drake.
Yeah, Tom Drake was one of the first to be prosecuted. And he's a hero too.
He is. Thank you. So that's it. We're going to move our live streams to Saturday
at 3 p.m. starting this Saturday. Because my running mate, Angela Walker,
driving a dump truck and they've got her working 14 hours a day,
instructions decent up. So she hasn't been able to make these Tuesday nights. So,
you know, check us out on Facebook and Twitter. We'll be here at three o'clock on Saturday.
And everybody can join us. So have a good evening everybody.
We've got